A Guide to the Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests, Series N FA323
Rockefeller Archive Center
Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Religious Interests, Series N
1894-1962
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
Rockefeller, David (1915-2017)
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman (1910-2004)
Rockefeller, John D., Jr. (John Davison) (1874-1960)
Rockefeller, John D., III (John Davison) (1906-1978)
FA323
40.06 Cubic Feet 106 containers
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The series is divided into twenty subseries, 11 of which are for specific churches, organizations, or movements. The sections are as follows:
American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, Baptist Organizations, Bible Societies, Christian Publications, Church Unity Radio Address, Churches, Federal Council of Churches of Christ in America, Fifth Avenue Baptist Church, Park Avenue Baptist Church, Interdenominational Cooperative Movement, Missionary and Church Groups, Protestant Council of the City of New York, Religious Education, Religious Organizations, Riverside Church, Salvation Army, Seamen's Church Institute, Billy Sunday, Young Men's Bible Class, Bibles, and Oversized materials.
Scope and Contents note
The Religious Interests series reflects the Rockefeller family's interest in and contributions to various churches and religious organizations. The files contain correspondence between members of the family and the family office, as well as officials and members of the various religious institutions. In some cases, the files include financial information on the appealing institutions. The miscellaneous files generally contain unsolicited appeals for donations. The series illustrates family contributions to religious organizations up to 1962. The contributions were made to a wide spectrum of organizations and activities, such as missionary movements, interdenominational cooperation, and religious education.
Except for John D. Rockefeller, Jr., these files do not provide information on the personal religious convictions of members of the Rockefeller family. John D. Rockefeller Jr.'s ideas on the Fatherhood of God and the Brotherhood of Man are well documented. These ideas are essential elements in understanding his continuing impact on religious organizations and thought.
Rockefeller family -- Art collections; State governments -- United States; Religious institutions; Restoration and conservation; Public welfare; Religion; Housing rehabilitation; Public relations; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Health insurance; Folk art; Government policy; Family planning; Federal government -- United States; Education; Education -- United States; World War II; World War I; Urban renewal; Urban policy; United States; Travel; International relations; International education; International economic relations; International cooperation; Medical care; Maternal health services; Juvenile delinquency; International relations -- United States; New York (N.Y.); Medical sciences; Medical research; Medical education; Performing arts; Parks -- New York (State); New York (State); Economic development; Art; Economics; Economic policy; Arts; Business; Art, Modern; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Charitable contributions; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Business enterprises, Foreign; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Capital investments; Child welfare; Civic improvement; Charities; Charities -- Investments; Philanthropy -- United States; Public health; Prohibition; Philanthropy; Public policy; Public health administration; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States
- American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
  - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, 1900-April 1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Attack by Dr. Gladden on John D. Rockefeller. Frederick T. Gates' notes on the origin of the controversy, references to chapter in John D. Rockefeller's book "The Difficult Art of Giving." Starr J. Murphy's article. Discussion. Gift to Board. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, John D. Rockefeller, Lawrence F. Abbott, William R. Harper, Starr J. Murphy, Rev. James L. Barton, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, May 1905-1906, 1910, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions - Pamphlets and Articles, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Printed materials, Mr. Montague's review of Miss Tarbell's "The History of the Standard Oil Company." Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, William R. Harper, Frederick T. Gates.
  - American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions - Clippings, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Baptist Organizations
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - General Correspondence, 1910-1922, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Society's needs, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s desire to contribute through church budget. John D. Rockefeller's contributions. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Thomas S. Barbour, Frederick T. Gates, Willard S. Richardson, George B. Huntington.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Judson College, Rangoon, 1928-1932, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Needs. John D. Rockefeller's contribution to help complete buildings. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution towards Judson Fund. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, P. H. J. Lerrigo, San Ba.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Japan Reconstruction Fund, July 1925, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Summary of earthquake losses in Japan, needs, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. gift. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, P. H. J. Lerrigo.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Mission Work - Assam, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Laura S. Rockefeller's gift to missionary work, chapel and hall at Madras and dormitory at Middle English School at South Tura, Assam. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, F. P. Haggard.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Missionary Education Movement, 1912-1913 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Report, John D. Rockefeller, Jr. desire not to contribute. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Rev. E. H. Cressy - East China Christian Education Association, 1924-1932 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to assist with fund for Physics Apparatus Fund and to secure Primary School supervisors. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Ernest D. Burton, Earl H. Cressy.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Rev. Joseph C. Robbins, 1916-1923, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Trip to India to survey American Baptist Foreign Mission Society work, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to pay expenses of trip, friendly sentiments. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Charles O. Heydt, Joseph C. Robbins, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Foreign Mission Society - Mr. Tsien, 1924-1929 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to pay tuition and living expenses of Mr. Tsien at the New York School of Social Work; Mr. Tsien's return to China and his employment at Yantsepoo Social Center. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Daniel H. Kulp II, D. Y. Tsien, Thomas B. Appleget.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society, 1894-1902 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    John D. Rockefeller's gift to Society used for instruction in Negro secondary schools; other pledges. Frederick T. Gates' memo about men selected for membership on proposed Finance Committee for Northern Baptist Convention, his appointment, resignation. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gift to aid home mission work in Puerto Rico. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, H. L. Morehouse, T. J. Morgan, Wallace Buttrick, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Harry Pratt Judson, John D. Rockefeller, C. L. White, Arthur W. Packard.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society, 1903-1908 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - General, 1909-1932, 1942-1943, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - Bishop College - Shaw University, 1902-1903 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Report. John D. Rockefeller's pledges. Correspondents include J. L. M. Curry, H. L. Morehouse, W. Buttrick.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - California Churches, 1906-1911 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    John D. Rockefeller's pledge to assist Baptist Churches in San Francisco destroyed by earthquake and fire, list of churches aided. Correspondents include H. L. Morehouse, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - Contributions, 1911-1920 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    John D. Rockefeller's pledges to budget of the American Baptist Home Mission Society. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, H. L. Morehouse, John D. Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, C. L. White.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - First Baptist Church, San Francisco, 1908-1910 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Needs, John D. Rockefeller's pledge for new building. Correspondents include H. L. Morehouse, Starr J. Murphy, George E. Burlingame.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - Puerto Rican School Building, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Laura S. Rockefeller's contribution to erect school building in Puerto Rico for training of ministers. Correspondents include H. L. Morehouse, Frederick T. Gates, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles O. Heydt.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home Mission Society - National Ministers' Institute, 1924-1935 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Plans for development of institutes for benefit of colored ministers in South, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge to assist in payment of expenses. Correspondents include G. S. Ford, Galen Fisher, Willard S. Richardson, Trevor Arnett, George R. Hovey.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Home and Foreign Mission Societies - Gifts, 1914-1933, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    John D. Rockefeller's gifts, pledges, conditions of gifts, to various organizations. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Bertram Cutler, Charles L. White, Charles O. Heydt, C. J. Rose.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Education Society, 1890-1900 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    John D. Rockefeller's pledges to colleges made through Society. Gifts to colleges. Correspondents include H. L. Morehouse, Frederick T. Gates, E. V. Cary, George D. Rogers.
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Education Society, 1901-1915 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Baptist Organizations - American Baptist Publication Society, 1900-1905, 1914-1924, 1932, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Needs. John D. Rockefeller's contribution to special fund to print the Scriptures in foreign tongues. Chapel Car work. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, Guy Lamson, Boston W. Smith.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Publishing Company - "The Baptist", 1930-1934 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Company's financial difficulties, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledge, merger of paper with The Christian Century, employment of Dr. Ashworth by National Conference of Christians and Jews. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Robert A. Ashworth, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., W. R. Conklin.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Church Extension Society of Brooklyn and Queens, 1896-1912 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    John D. Rockefeller's pledge to Society, renewal. Brooklyn religious needs. Establishment of Trust, Bankers' Trust Company as Trustee, pledges through Rockefeller Foundation. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Frederick T. Gates, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., H. L. Morehouse, Starr J. Murphy, Henry E. Drake, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas M. Debevoise, C. H. Sears, J. B. Colgate, O. R. Judd, W. R. Conklin.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Church Extension Society of Brooklyn and Queens, 1913-1918, 1927, 1938, 1941, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Church Extension Society of Brooklyn and Queens - Forward Movement, 1917, 1904-1907, 1917-1920 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    John D. Rockefeller's contribution. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Fresh Air Home Society, 1900-1935, 1944, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    John D. Rockefeller's contributions. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. Subscription to Baptist Young People's Union of New York City. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., William M. Crane, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Stanley B. Hazzard, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, W. R. Conklin.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Home for the Aged, New York, 1900-1924, 1935-1942, 1948-1953 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    John D. Rockefeller's annual contribution. Laura Spelman Rockefeller's trust created for Baptist Home Society of City of New York, her gifts. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., E. V. Cary, H. Sims, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Charles O. Heydt, W. H. Hays, Rev. C. Woelfkin.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Home for the Aged, New York - Clarke Drinking Fountain Memorial and Painting, 1931-1932 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Proposal to substitute painting of the Sistine Madonna for window at chapel; (painting loaned by John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to Women's Room at Park Avenue Church); drinking fountain installed as memorial to Mr. and Mrs. Clarke's mother. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Marshall Clarke, Augustus N. Allen.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Home for the Aged, New York - Gift, December 24, 1929 for Furnishing, 1929-1930 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    John D. Rockefeller's contribution for furnishing and equipping auditorium and infirmary at Home in memory of wife. Willard S. Richardson, A. N. Allen, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Home for the Aged, New York - John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Contributions, 1905-1913, 1919-1920, 1927-1933, 1938-1942 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Annual contributions to Home, to Golden Jubilee Fund, contributions in Mrs. Rockefeller's name, others. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Ministers' Home Society, 1894, 1902-1916 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    John D. Rockefeller's contributions to Society of Aged and Infirm Ministers. Contributions of Laura Spelman Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller. Correspondents include M. H. Pogson, John D. Rockefeller, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson, Charles O. Heydt, W. B. Matteson, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Home of Northern Ohio - Gift from John D. Rockefeller, Jr., 1907-1951 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    General note
    Actual dates for this Folder are 1907-1908, 1912-1919, 1923-1926, 1929, 1935, 1939-1940, 1951.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Missionary Convention of New York, 1894-1914 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    John D. Rockefeller's subscription, desire that fund not be used toward new Brighton church or the Niagara Falls Church. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions to annual budgets, pledge to Revolving Fund. Correspondents include H. W. Barnes, Frederick T. Gates, George D. Rogers, E. V. Cary, Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, O. R. Judd, Willard S. Richardson, A. W. Beaven, W. A. Granger, N. W. Davis, John E. Smith, Thomas M. Debevoise, Harvey F. Remington.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Missionary Convention of New York, 1915-1919, 1925-1942 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Negro Educational Center, New York City, 1942-1960 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution to be applied to general program of Negro Education Center, renewal of pledges until stopped in 1960 by Martha B. Rockefeller. Correspondents include Arthur W. Packard, C. H. Sears, F. P. Hazzard, Dana S. Creel.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Union of Western Canada - Brandon College, 1903-1919, 1926-1929 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    Historical statement about Brandon College, Brandon Manitoba; request from college and Baptist missionary work in Canadian Northwest for assistance; John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. John D. Rockefeller's contributions. Pledge for Church Edifice. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, A. J. Vining, Charles A. Eaton, John D. Rockefeller, Willard S. Richardson, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Young People's Union of Ohio, 1900-1904, 1907-1908 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    Appeal for funds, John D. Rockefeller's contributions. Hiawatha Lake Assembly. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, George D. Rogers, Starr J. Murphy, Charles O. Heydt, H. G. Baldwin, C. J. Rose.
  - Baptist Organizations - Miscellaneous, 1902-1960 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    Baptist Social Union of New York. Election of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. as member, pledge to Membership Campaign Fund, declination of invitations to dinner. Correspondents include Charles Evans Hughes, Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Ballard.
  - Baptist Organizations - Baptist Seminary in Ireland, 1927, 1931 (Box 6, Folder 43)
    Fund for Irish Baptist College, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Eugene C. Carder, J. B. Colgate.
  - Baptist Organizations - Boston Baptist Social Union, 1926-1939, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 43A)
    Construction of new building by Dudley Street Baptist Church of Boston, John D. Rockefeller's contribution, terms of gift; personal gifts to minister. John D. Rockefeller Jr.'s contributions. Reports. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Charles W. Bailey, Willard S. Richardson, Robert W. Gumbel, Rev. Arthur T. Brooks, Alvan T. Fuller, W. H. Bowler.
  - Baptist Organizations - Cleveland Baptist City Mission Society, 1899-1918 (Box 6, Folder 44)
    Articles of Incorporation, John D. Rockefeller's pledge to Society for reduction of mortgage indebtedness, renewal of pledge. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, John D. Rockefeller, Charles F. Lang, Charles A. Brooks.
  - Baptist Organizations - Cleveland Baptist Association, 1928-1937 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    Fund for new churches and for securing trained leaders, John D. Rockefeller's contribution, other gifts, plans for centennial celebration, plans for survey of Euclid Avenue Baptist Church. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gifts. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, Trevor Arnett, John D. Rockefeller, D. R. Sharpe, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Baptist Organizations - Cleveland Baptist Association, 1937-1942, 1953-1954, 1957-1960 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Baptist Organizations - New Jersey Baptist Convention, 1893-1894, 1897-1920, 1926-1931 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    John D. Rockefeller's contributions. Reports, financial and others. Gradual reduction of contributions. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Robert W. Gumbel, Delavan Dewolf, Willard S. Richardson, Frederick T. Gates.
  - Baptist Organizations - New York City Baptist Mission Society - General, 1899-1910 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    Plans for "Forward Movement." Reports. John D. Rockefeller's contributions. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s statement favoring Society's aims. Grace Church. Italian Mission work. Tremont Property. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Starr J. Murphy, J. M. Colgate, Edward Judson, C. H. Sears, E. L. Ballard, Willard S. Richardson, Frederick T. Gates, Charles F. Aked, William H. Hays.
  - Baptist Organizations - New York City Baptist Mission Society - General, 1911-1918, 1925-1935 (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Baptist Organizations - New York City Baptist Mission Society - Judson Memorial Fund, 1914-1920 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    Contributions, Sullivan Street House, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gift. Property on West 3rd Street. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller's contributions toward Judson Memorial Neighborhood House Budget. Correspondents include Starr J. Murphy, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Willard S. Richardson, A. L. Chipman, Paul B. Stephan.
  - Baptist Organizations - New York City Baptist Mission Society - Gift of June 26, 1922, 1921-1926, 1932, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 51)
  - Baptist Organizations - New York Baptist City Society, 1930-1957 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    Appeals. John D. Rockefeller 3rd's declination. David Rockefeller's contribution. Condition of 1922 pledge. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller 3rd, John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Stanley B. Hazzard, C. H. Sears, W. R. Conklin, Dana S. Creel, Yorke Allen.
    Open per KWR, December 2004.
  - Baptist Organizations - New York Baptist City Society, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 52A)
  - Baptist Organizations - Pennsylvania Baptist State Mission Society, 1896-1919 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    John D. Rockefeller's contributions. Uses to which funds were kept. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, N. H. Conard, C. A. Sears, Starr J. Murphy, Willard S. Richardson.
  - Baptist Organizations - The Watchman-Examiner, 1907, 1911-1914, 1919, 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    Request for financial assistance, death of Cicero B. Curtis. Correspondents include John D. Rockefeller, Frederick T. Gates, Thomas O. Conant, Wallace Buttrick, E. L. Ballard.
  - Baptist Organizations - Woman's American Baptist Home Mission Society, 1924-1935, 1941, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    Gift from Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial Fund. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contribution in the name of his mother, pledge to Golden Anniversary Fund. Correspondents include Willard S. Richardson, John D. Rockefeller, Bertram Cutler, Raymond B. Fosdick.
  - Baptist Organizations - Woman's American Baptist Foreign Mission Society, 1901, 1912, 1915-1916, 1919-1928, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    Includes Women's Union Christian Colleges of Orient. Frederick T. Gates' memo opposing endowment funds, Laura S. Rockefeller's gift for Home for Children of Missionaries at Newton Center and Jubilee Fund, John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s contributions. Correspondents include Frederick T. Gates, Willard S. Richardson, Thomas M. Debevoise.
  - Baptist Organizations - Northern Baptist Convention - General, 1912-1925 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    Financial data showing percentage of John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s gifts to total donation receipts. Change of Convention's name to American Baptist Convention. Three Million Dollar Campaign. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s pledges.